Chapter 48. The first lowering.
The phantoms, for so they seemed, were flitting on the other side of the deck,
and with a noiseless solarity, were casting loose the tackles and bands of
the boat which swung there. This boat had always been deemed one of the spare
boats, though technically called the captain's on account of its hanging from
the starboard quarter. The figure that now stood by its boughs was tall and
swart with one white tooth evily protruding from its steel-like lips. A
rumpled Chinese jacket of black cotton ferurially invested him with wide black
trousers of the same dark stuff. But strangely crowning this ebbaness was a
glistening white pleated turban, the living hair braided and coiled round and
round upon his head. Less swar in aspect, the companions of this figure
were of that vivid tiger yellow complexion peculiar to some of the
aboriginal natives of the Manilas, a race notorious for a certain diabolism
of subtlety, and by some honest white mariners supposed to be the paid spies
and secret confidential agents on the water of the devil, their lord, whose
counting room they supposed to be elsewhere.
While yet the wandering ship's company were gazing upon these strangers, Ahab
cried out to the white turbaned old man at their head. Already there, Fidala.
Ready, was the half-hissed reply. Lower away then, do you hear? Shouting across
the deck. Lower away there, I say.
Such was the thunder of his voice that spite of their amazement, the men sprang
over the rail, the sheav whirled around in the blocks. With a wallow, the three
boats dropped into the sea, while with a dextrous off-handed daring unknown in
any other vocation, the sailors, goatlike, leaped down the rolling ship's
side into the tossed boats below.
Hardly had they pulled out from under the ship's lee when a fourth keel coming
from the windward side pulled round under the stern and showed the five
strangers rowing Ahab who standing erect in the stern loudly hailed Starbucks
stub and flask to spread themselves widely so as to cover a large expanse of
water. But with all their eyes again riveted upon the swart Fidala and his
crew, the inmates of the other boats obeyed not the command. "Captain Ahab,"
said Starbucks. "Spread yourselves!"
cried Ahab. "Give way all four boats!
Thou flask! Pull out more to Lord."
"I I sir," cheerfully cried little kingpost, sweeping round his great
steering ore. "Lay back!" addressing his crew. There, there, there again. There
she blows right ahead, boys. Lay back.
Never heed yonder yellow boys, Archie.
Oh, I don't mind him, sir, said Archie.
I knew it all before now. Didn't I hear him in the hold? And didn't I tell
Kabako here of it? What say you, Kabako?
There are stowways, Mr. Flask.
Pull, pull, my fine hearts alive. Pull, my children. Pull my little ones.
Drawlingly and soothingly sighed stubbed his crew, some of whom still showed
signs of uneasiness. Why don't you break your backbones, my boys? What is it you
stare at? Those chaps in yonder boat.
There are only five more hands come to help us. Never mind from where. The more
the merrier. Pull then. Do pull. Never mind the brimstone. Devils are good
fellows enough. So, so there you are now. That's the stroke for £1,000.
That's the stroke to sweep the stakes.
Hurrah for the gold cup of sperm oil, my heroes. Three cheers, men. All hearts
alive. Easy, easy. Don't be in a hurry.
Don't be in a hurry. Why don't you snap your roars, you rascals, bite something,
you dogs. So, so, so then, softly, softly. That's it. That's it. Long and
strong. Give way there. Give way. The devil fetch you. You rag them up and
wrap scallions. You're all asleep. Stop snoring, you sleepers, and pull. Pull.
Will you pull? Can't you pull? Won't you? Why, in the name of gudgeons and
ginger cakes, don't you pull? Pull and break something. Pull and start your
eyes out here. Whipping out the sharp knife from his girdle. Every mother's
son of you draw his knife and pull with the blade between your teeth. That's it.
That's it. Now you do something. That looks like it. My steel bits. Starter.
Starter. My silver spoons. Starter.
Marlin spikes.
Stub's exordium to his crew is given here at large because he had a rather
peculiar way of talking to them in general, and especially in inculcating
the religion of rowing. But you must not suppose from this specimen of his
sermonizings that he ever flew into downright passions with his
congregation. Not at all, and therein consisted his chief peculiarity. He
would say the most horrific things to his crew in a tone so strangely
compounded of fun and fury, and the fury seemed so calculated merely as a spice
to the fun that no orsman could hear such queer invocations without pulling
for dear life, and yet pulling for the mere joke of the thing. Besides, he all
the time looked so easy and indolent himself, so loungingly managed his
steering ore, and so broadly gaped, open-mouthed at times, that the mere
sight of such a yawning commander, by sheer force of contrast, acted like a
charm upon the crew. Then again, Stub was one of those odd sort of humorists,
whose jolly is sometimes so curiously ambiguous as to put all inferiors on
their guard in the matter of obeying them.
In obedience to a sign from Ahab, Starbucks was now pulling obliquely
across Stub's bow, and when, for a minute or so the two boats were pretty
near to each other, Stub hailed the mate. "Mr. Starbucks, lar boat there.
Ahoy! A word with you, sir, if you please."
Hello," returned Starbucks, turning round not a single inch as he spoke,
still earnestly but whisperingly urging his crew, his face set like a flint from stubs.
"What? Think you of those yellow boys, sir," smuggled on board somehow before the
ship sailed. "Strong, strong boys!" in a whisper to his crew, then speaking out
loud again. "A sad business, Mr. Stub.
Seether, seether, my lads. But never mind, Mr. Stub. All for the best. Let
your crew pull strong. Come what will.
Spring, my men. Spring. There's hogs heads of sperm ahead, Mr. Stub. And
that's what you came for. Pull, my boys.
Sperm. Sperm's the play. This at least is duty. Duty and profit hand in hand.
I I I thought as much siloquised stub when the boats diverged. As soon as I
clapped I on him, I thought so. I I That's what he went into the afterhold
for so often, as Doughboy long suspected. They were hidden down there.
The white whales at the bottom of it.
Well, well, so be it. Can't be helped.
All right, give way, men. It ain't the white whale today. Give way.
Now, the advent of these outlandish strangers at such a critical instant as
the lowering of the boats from the deck, this had not unreasonably awakened a
sort of superstitious amazement in some of the ship's company. But Archie's
fancied discovery, having some time previous got abroad among them, though
indeed not credited then, this had, in some small measure prepared them for the
event. It took off the extreme edge of their wonder. So what with all this and
Stub's confident way of accounting for their appearance, they were for the time
freed from superstitious surmisings, though the affair still left abundant
room for all manner of wild conjectures as to Dark Ahab's precise agency in the
matter from the beginning. For me, I silently recalled the mysterious shadows
I had seen creeping on board the Peekquad during the dim Nantucket dawn,
as well as the enigmatical hintings of the unaccountable Elijah.
Meanwhile, Ahab, out of hearing of his officers, having cided the furthest to
windward, was still ranging ahead of the other boats, a circumstance bespeaking
how potent a crew was pulling him. Those tiger yellow creatures of his seemed all
steel and whale bone. Like five tripammers, they rose and fell with
regular strokes of strength, which periodically started the boat along the
water like a horizontal burst boiler out of a Mississippi steamer. As for Fidala,
who was seen pulling the harpooner ore, he had thrown aside his black jacket and
displayed his naked chest with the whole part of his body above the gunnel,
clearly cut against the alternating depressions of the watery horizon. While
at the other end of the boat, Ahab, with one arm like a fencers thrown half
backward into the air, as if to counterbalance any tendency to trip,
Ahab was seen steadily managing his steering ore, as in a thousand boat
lowerings there the white whale had torn him. All at once the outstretched arm
gave a peculiar motion and then remained fixed, while the boat's five oars were
seen simultaneously peaked. Boat and crew sat motionless on the sea.
Instantly, the three spread boats in the rear paused on their way. The whales had
irregularly settled bodily down into the blue, thus giving no distantly
discernable token of the movement, though from his closer vicinity Ahab had observed it.
Every man, look out along his oars, cried Starbucks. Thou Quequ stand up.
Nimbily springing up on the triangular raised box in the bow, the savage stood
erect there, and with intensely eager eyes gazed off towards the spot where
the chase had last been described.
Likewise, upon the extreme stern of the boat, where it was also triangularly
platformed level with the gunnel, Starbucks himself was seen coolly and
adroitly balancing himself to the jerking tossings of his chip of a craft,
and silently eyeing the vast blue eye of the sea. Not very far distant, Flask's
boat was also lying breathlessly still, its commander recklessly standing upon
the top of the logger head, a stout sort of post rooted in the keel and rising
some 2 ft above the level of the stern platform. It is used for catching turns
with the whale line. Its top is not more spacious than the palm of a man's hand,
and standing upon such a base as that, flask seemed perched at the mast head of
some ship which had sunk to all but her trucks. But Little Kingpost was small
and short, and at the same time Little Kingpost was full of a large and tall
ambition, so that this loggerhead standpoint of his did by no means satisfy Kingpost.
I can't see three C's off. Tip us up an
ore there, and let me on to that." Upon this dagu, with either hand upon the
gunnel to steady his way, swiftly slid after, and then, erecting himself,
volunteered his lofty shoulders for a pedestal. Good amassed head as any, sir.
Will you mount? That I will, and thank you very much, my fine fellow, only I
wish you 50 ft taller. whereupon planting his feet firmly against two
opposite planks of the boat, the gigantic negro, stooping a little,
presented his flat palm to Flask's foot, and then putting Flask's hand on his
hearseplumed head, and bidding him spring, as he himself should toss, with
one dextrous fling, landed the little man high and dry on his shoulders. And
here was Flask, now standing, Dagu, with one lifted arm, furnishing him with a
breast band to lean against and steady himself by.
At any time, it is a strange sight to the Tyro to see with what wondrous
habitude of unconscious skill the whaleman will maintain an erect posture
in his boat, even when pitched about by the most riotously perverse and
crossrunn seas. still more strange to see him giddily perched upon the
loggerhead itself under such circumstances. But the sight of little
flask mounted upon gigantic dagu was yet more curious for sustaining himself with
a cool indifferent easy unthought of barbaric majesty. The noble negro to
every role of the sea harmoniously rolled his fine form. On his broad back
flax andhaired flask seemed a snowflake.
The bearer looked nobler than the rider, though truly vivaceious, tumultuous,
ostentatious little flask would now and then stamp with impatience. But not one
added heave did he thereby give to the Negro's lordly chest. So have I seen
passion and vanity stamping the living magnanimous earth, but the earth did not
alter her tides and her seasons for that. Meanwhile, Stub, the third mate,
betrayed no such far-gazing solicitudes.
The whales might have made one of their regular soundings, not a temporary dive
for mere fright, and if that were the case, Stub, as his want, in such cases,
it seems, was resolved to solace the languishing interval with his pipe. He
withdrew it from his hatband, where he always wore it a slant like a feather.
He loaded it and rammed home the loading with his thumb end. But hardly had he
ignited his match across the rough sandpaper of his hand, when Tashego, his
harpooner, whose eyes had been setting too windward like two fixed stars,
suddenly dropped like light from his erect attitude to his seat, crying out
in a quick frenzy of hurry, "Down! Down all, and give way! There they are!"
To a landsman, no whale, nor any sign of a herring, would have been visible at
that moment. Nothing but a troubled bit of greenish white water and thin,
scattered puffs of vapor hovering over it, and suffusingly blowing off to lured
like the confused scud from white rolling billows. The air around suddenly
vibrated and tingled, as it were, like the air over intensely heated plates of
iron. Beneath this atmospheric waving and curling, and partially beneath a
thin layer of water, also the whales were swimming, seen in advance of all
the other indications, the puffs of vapor they spouted, seemed their
forerunning couriers and detached flying outr rididers. All four boats were now
in keen pursuit of that one spot of troubled water and air, but it bad fair
to outstrip them. It flew on and on as a mass of interblending bubbles borne down
a rapid stream from the hills. "Pull, pull, my good boys," said Starbucks in
the lowest possible but intensest concentrated whisper to his men, while
the sharp fixed glance from his eyes darted straight ahead of the bow almost
seemed as two visible needles in two unairring binnacle compasses. He did not
say much to his crew, though, nor did his crew say anything to him. Only the
silence of the boat was at intervals startlingly pierced by one of his
peculiar whispers, now harsh with command, now soft with intreaty.
How different the loud little kingpost.
Sing out and say something, my hearties.
Roar and pull, my thunderbolts. Beach me. Beach me on their black backs, boys.
Only do that for me and I'll sign over to you my Martha's Vineyard plantation
boys, including wife and children, boys.
Lay me on. Lay me on. Oh Lord, Lord, but I shall go stark staring mad. See, see
that white water. And so shouting, he pulled his hat from his head and stamped
up and down on it, then picking it up, flirted it far off upon the sea, and
finally fell to rearing and plunging in the boat's stern like a crazed colt from the prairie.
Look at that chap now, philosophically drawled stub, who, with his unlighted
short pipe, mechanically retained between his teeth at a short distance,
followed after. He's got fits. That flask has fits. Yes. Give him fits.
That's the very word. Pitch Fitz into them. Merrily, merrily, hearts alive.
Pudding for supper. You know, Mary's the word. Pull, babes. Pull, sucklings. Pull
all. But what the devil are you hurrying about? Softly, softly, and steadily, my
men. Only pull and keep pulling. Nothing more. Crack all your backbones and bite
your knives in two, that's all. Take it easy. Why don't you take it easy, I say?
And burst all your livers and lungs.
But what it was that inscrable Ahab said to that tiger yellow crew of his, these
were words best omitted here. For you live under the blessed light of the
evangelical land. Only the infidel sharks in the audacious seas may give
ear to such words, when, with tornado brow and eyes of red murder and foam
glued lips, Ahab leaped after his prey.
Meanwhile, all the boats tore on, the repeated specific illusions of flask to
that whale, as he called the fictitious monster which he declared to be
incessantly tantalizing his boat's bow with its tail. These allusions of his
were at times so vivid and lifelike that they would cause some one or two of his
men to snatch a fearful look over the shoulder. But this was against all rule,
for the oresmen must put out their eyes and ram a skewer through their necks,
usage pronouncing that they must have no organs but ears and no limbs but arms in
these critical moments.
It was a sight full of quick wonder and awe. The vast swells of the omnipotent
sea, the surging hollow roar they made as they rolled along the eight gunnels
like gigantic bulls in a boundless bowling green. The brief suspended agony
of the boat as it would tip for an instant on the knifelike edge of the
sharper waves that almost seemed threatening to cut it in two. the sudden
profound dip into the watery glenns and hollows, the keen spurrings and goatings
to gain the top of the opposite hill, the headlong sled-like slide down its
other side. All these, with the cries of the headsmen and harpooners, and the
shuddering gasps of the oresman, with the wondrous sight of the ivory peekquad
bearing down upon her boats with outstretched sails, like a wild hen
after her screaming brood. All this was thrilling. Not the raw recruit marching
from the bosom of his wife into the fever heat of his first battle. Not the
dead man's ghost encountering the first unknown phantom in the other world.
Neither of these can feel stranger and stronger emotions than that man does who
for the first time finds himself pulling into the charmed churn circle of the
hunted sperm whale.
The dancing white water made by the chase was now becoming more and more
visible, owing to the increasing darkness of the dun cloud shadows flung
upon the sea. The jets of vapor no longer blended, but tilted everywhere to
right and left. The whales seemed separating their wakes. The boats were
pulled more apart, Starbucks giving chase to three whales running dead to
lured. Our sail was now set, and with the still rising wind, we rushed along.
The boat going with such madness through the water that the lee oars could
scarcely be worked rapidly enough to escape being torn from the rollocks.
Soon we were running through a suffusing wide veil of mist, neither ship nor boat
to be seen. "Give way, men," whispered Starbucks, drawing still further aft the
sheet of his sail. "There is time to kill a fish yet before the squall comes.
There's white water again, close to spring.
Soon after, two cries in quick succession on each side of us denoted
that the other boats had got fast, but hardly were they overheard when, with a
lightninglike hurtling whisper, Starbucks said, "Stand up!" And
Quiquake, harpoon in hand, sprang to his feet. Though not one of the oresmen was
then facing the life and death peril so close to them ahead, yet with their eyes
on the intense countenance of the mate in the stern of the boat, they knew that
the imminent instant had come. They heard, too an enormous wallowing sound,
as of 50 elephants stirring in their litter. Meanwhile, the boat was still
booming through the mist, the waves curling and hissing around us like the
erected crests of enraged serpents.
That's his hump there. There. Give it to him, whispered Starbucks. A short
rushing sound leaped out of the boat. It was the darted iron of Quiquake. Then,
all in one welded commotion came an invisible push from a stern, while
forward the boat seemed striking on a ledge. The sail collapsed and exploded.
A gush of scalding vapor shot up nearby.
Something rolled and tumbled like an earthquake beneath us. The whole crew
were half suffocated as they were tossed helter skelter into the white curdling
cream of the squall. Squall, whale, and harpoon had all blended together, and
the whale, merely grazed by the iron, escaped.
Though completely swamped, the boat was nearly unharmed. Swimming round it, we
picked up the floating oes, and lashing them across the gunnel, tumbled back to
our places. There we sat up to our knees in the sea, the water covering every rib
and plank, so that to our downward gazing eyes the suspended craft seemed a
coral boat grown up to us from the bottom of the ocean. The wind increased
to a howl. The waves dashed their bucklers together. The whole squall
roared, forked, and crackled around us like a white fire upon the prairies, in
which unconsumed we were burning, immortal in these jaws of death. In vain
we hailed the other boats, as well roar to the live coals down the chimney of a
flaming furnace as hail those boats in that storm. Meanwhile, the driving scud,
rack, and mist grew darker with the shadows of night. No sign of the ship
could be seen. The rising sea forbad all attempts to bail out the boat. The ores
were useless as propellers, performing now the office of life preservers. So
cutting the lashing of the waterproof match keg, after many failures,
Starbucks contrived to ignite the lamp in the lantern. Then stretching it on a
waifole, handed it to Quiquake as the standard bearer of this forlorn hope.
There, then he sat, holding up that imbecile candle in the heart of that almighty forlornness.
There then he sat the sign and symbol of a man without faith, hopelessly holding
up hope in the midst of despair.
Wet, drenched through, and shivering cold, desparing of ship or boat, we
lifted our eyes as the dawn came on, the mist still spread over the sea, the
empty lantern lay crushed in the bottom of the boat. Suddenly, Quiquake started
to his feet, hollowing his hand to his ear. We all heard a faint creaking as of
ropes and yards hitherto muffled by the storm. The sound came nearer and nearer.
The thick mists were dimly parted by a huge vague form. A frighted we all
sprang into the sea as the ship at last loomed into view, bearing right down
upon us within a distance not much more than its length.
Floating on the waves, we saw the abandoned boat, as for one instant it
tossed and gaped beneath the ship's boughs like a chip at the base of a
cataract, and then the vast hull rolled over it, and it was seen no more till it
came up weltering a stern. Again we swam for it, were dashed against it by the
seas, and were at last taken up, and safely landed on board. Air the squall
came close, too. of the other boats had cut loose from their fish and returned
to the ship in good time. The ship had given us up, but was still cruising, if
happily it might light upon some token of our perishing, an ore or a lance pole.